Guide to the Records of the New York Foundling Hospital 1869-2009 MS 347
New-York Historical Society
- Series III - Administrative Records, Chronological, 1869-2004
  - "The New York Foundling Child Development Project" - Report by Michael Garber, Director Community Program Development, circa 1974 (Offsite-box 123, Volume 240)
  - Miscellaneous reports (1974-1977), memos (1977-1979), 1974-1979 (Offsite-box 16, Folder 2)
  - 5-Year Plan - memos and related materials, 1975 (Offsite-box 16, Folder 3)
  - Manual: "Practical Approaches to Management of Child Maltreatment", 1975 (Offsite-box 16, Folder 4)
  - Certificate of Merger - St. Agatha into NY Foundling Hospital, 1977 May 25 (Offsite-box 16, Folder 5)
  - Pharmacy Policies Manual, circa 1977 (Offsite-box 16, Folder 6)
  - N.Y.S. O.M.R.D.D. - Interagency transfer project and conversion of critical care programs to intermediate care - memos, correspondence, reports, agreement, circa 1977 - 1984 (Offsite-box 16, Folder 7)
  - Lease of space at 1175 Third Avenue to Hunter College and related correspondence, 1978 November 15 - 1981 September 28 (Offsite-box 16, Folder 8)
  - Child Welfare Reform Act - reports, memos, 1979 March - 1982 June (Offsite-box 16, Folder 9)
  - 5-Year Strategic Plan by Michael Garber - 2 copies (1 annotated) and notes on plan, 1979 June (Offsite-box 16, Folder 10)
  - Certificate of Amendment of Certificate of Incorporation, 1979 October 11 (Offsite-box 16, Folder 11)
  - Policy Statements, circa 1979-1987 (Offsite-box 16, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence - State Department of Social Services, 1980 February - 1981 September (Offsite-box 16, Folder 13)
  - 5-Year Strategic Plan, 1980 September (Offsite-box 16, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence and other materials collected and arranged by Sisters of Charity, 1980-1989 (Offsite-box 16, Folder 15)
  - Agency Philosophy, 1981 May (Offsite-box 16, Folder 16)
  - Description of all Foundling programs, and administrative responsibility chart, 1981 December and 1982 November (Offsite-box 16, Folder 17)
  - Correspondence - State Department of Social Services, 1982 February - 1984 December (Offsite-box 17, Folder 1)
  - Mental Hygiene Program Development, 1983 February - 1985 October (Offsite-box 17, Folder 2)
  - Foundling response to NYC Human Resources Administration Questionnaire on Congregate Care, 1983 March (Offsite-box 17, Folder 3)
  - Agency Manual - Drafts and Memos, 1983 April - 1984 January and undated (Offsite-box 17, Folder 4)
  - Miscellaneous Program Ideas, 1983 May - 1984 March and undated (Offsite-box 17, Folder 5)
  - Agency Manual - 2 draft typescripts, 1984 January (Offsite-box 17, Folder 6)
  - Agency Manual, 1984 January (Offsite-box 17, Folder 7)
  - 590 Avenue of the Americas - Floor Plan, Building Permit, Certificate of Occupancy and Related Materials, 1984 February 27 - 1988 January 25 (Offsite-box 17, Folder 8)
  - Program Development, 1984-1986 and 1998 (Offsite-box 17, Folder 9)
  - 1985 Agency Goals, 1984 November - 1985 October (Offsite-box 17, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence - State Department of Social Services, 1985 February - 1988 December (Offsite-box 17, Folder 11)
  - Grant proposal: Factors impacting on teen mothering, 1985 April - September (Offsite-box 17, Folder 12)
  - Memos of the Planning Group, 1985 June - December (Offsite-box 17, Folder 13)
  - 1985-1990 Strategic Plan (2 copies), 1985 July (Offsite-box 18, Folder 1)
  - Report on 1175 Third Avenue by James Felt Realty Services, 1985 September 13 (Offsite-box 18, Folder 2)
  - Sale of 1175 Third Avenue to Donald J. Trump, December 30-31, 1985 (bound documents and interleaved correspondence), 1985 October 16 - December 31 (Offsite-box 80, Volume 23)
  - Report on Strategic Planning Process, 1986 May 16 (Offsite-box 18, Folder 3)
  - Support Services Manual, 1987 (Offsite-box 18, Folder 4)
  - 590 Avenue of the Americas -new building miscellaneous materials, circa 1987-1988 (Offsite-box 18, Folder 5)
  - Ribbon cutting and dedication ceremonies for 590 Avenue of the Americas - correspondence, fliers, invitations, programs, 1988 March 11 - 1989 May 18 (Offsite-box 18, Folder 6)
  - Position paper on AIDS, 1988 March 18 (Offsite-box 18, Folder 7)
  - "The Foundling children fare-well notes to the neighborhood" assembled by Grandma Anna for Sister Madeline, 1988 June-August (Offsite-box 18, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence - Sister Marilda Joseph Aiello to Sister Marie Catherine Blaine et.al. chronicling move from 1175 Third Avenue to 590 Avenue of the Americas, folder 1 of 5, 1988 June 4 - 1988 October 22 (Offsite-box 18, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence - Sister Marilda Joseph Aiello to Sister Marie Catherine Blaine et.al., folder 2 of 5, 1988 October 24 - 1988 December 31 (Offsite-box 18, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence - Sister Marilda Joseph Aiello to Sister Marie Catherine Blaine et.al. - folder 3 of 5, 1989 January 2 - 1989 April 29 (Offsite-box 18, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence - Sister Marilda Joseph Aiello to Sister Marie Catherine Blaine et.al., folder 4 of 5, 1989 May 1 - 1989 August 19 (Offsite-box 18, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence - Sister Marilda Joseph Aiello to Sister Marie Catherine Blaine et.al., folder 5 of 5, 1989 August 21 - 1990 August 1 (Offsite-box 19, Folder 1)
  - Housing Position Paper, 1989 January 31 (Offsite-box 19, Folder 2)
  - NY State Dept. of Social Services Homeless Housing and Assistance Program project application - sister Cecilia Schneider Community Housing Services, 1989 (Offsite-box 19, Folder 3)
  - 1990-1995 Strategic Plan - memos, reports, committee minutes, 1989 October - 1994 February (Offsite-box 19, Folder 4)
  - Memos and correspondence re: Wilder vs. Bernstein/Wilder Classification System, 1989 December - 1990 November (Offsite-box 19, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, memos, and grant proposals with Altman Foundation, Alfred E. Smith Foundation, Caldor Foundation, 1990-1993 (Offsite-box 19, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence collected and arranged by Sisters of Charity, 1990-1995 (Offsite-box 19, Folder 7)
  - Programs and Services - miscellaneous materials, 1990 October - 1992 November (Offsite-box 19, Folder 8)
  - Certificate of Amendment of Certificate of Incorporation, 1991 February 19 (Offsite-box 19, Folder 9)
  - Mission Effectiveness Committee, circa 1990-1991 (Offsite-box 19, Folder 10)
  - Mission Statement Committee, 1991-1996 (Offsite-box 19, Folder 11)
  - Programs and Services, 1992 June (Offsite-box 19, Folder 12)
  - Strategic Planning Report 1994-1997 (2 copies) (Offsite-box 20, Folder 1)
  - Family and Community Centered Services Pilot Proposal, circa 1994 (Offsite-box 20, Folder 2)
  - Proclamation by Borough President Ruth Messinger: "New York Foundling Hospital Day" (oversize), 1995 April 25 (Offsite-box OS 1, Folder 4)
  - Layoffs and cutbacks, 1995 June (Offsite-box 20, Folder 3)
  - Integrated Marketing Communications Plan and Related Donation Appeals, 1995 June-December (Offsite-box 20, Folder 4)
  - Strategic Planning Committee Recommendations, 1995 September 12 (Offsite-box 20, Folder 5)
  - Child Care Manual, 1996 January (Offsite-box 20, Folder 6)
  - Strategic Planning 1997-2000, 1996 August - 1997 July (Offsite-box 20, Folder 7)
  - Strategic Planning Committee newsletters, 1996 November - 1997 October (Offsite-box 20, Folder 8)
  - "Child Welfare Organizations" report by Michael Garber and Kathleen McGlade, circa 1997 (Offsite-box 20, Folder 9)
  - Michael Garber correspondence with Sisters of Charity and miscellaneous memos to staff, 1997, 1999 (Offsite-box 20, Folder 10)
  - NYF book project - correspondence and related materials, 1998 March 2 - October 6, and 2000 July 18 (Offsite-box 20, Folder 11)
  - Maps showing locations of Foundling outreach programs, 1998 (Offsite-box 20, Folder 12)
  - Safety Committee Meeting Minutes, 1999 May-August (Offsite-box 20, Folder 13)
  - NYF Year 2000 Command Center Manual, 1999 December (Offsite-box 20, Folder 14)
  - NYF Year 2000 Regional Command Center Manual and updates, 1999 December - 2000 September (Offsite-box 20, Folder 15)
  - Directory of Programs and Services (2 copies), 2000 January (Offsite-box 20, Folder 16)
  - Reports: "Conceptual Framework for Parent Participation" (Michael Garber, Kathy McGlade, Joe Ackerman) and "The Changing Role of Parents in Child Welfare Agencies" (Garber) and related correspondence, 2000 April-August and undated (Offsite-box 20, Folder 17)
  - Certificate of Amendment of Certificate of Incorporation, 2004 November 5 (Offsite-box 20, Folder 18)
- Series IV - Centers, Programs and Departments, Alphabetical, 1869-2008
  This series consists of 47 subseries, arranged alphabetically by program, center or department, using categories created mostly by Sister Marilda Joseph Aiello or by other representatives of the Foundling. Many subseries contain only a few folders, or sometimes a single folder, of material. Materials include correspondence, proposals, reports, pamphlets or brochures, and clippings. Many subseries contain photographic prints, arranged at the end of the subseries.
  The bulk of the individual programs collected in this series were initiated in the 1970's-1990's. There are, however, significant exceptions, including the Boarding Department and the Ladies Auxiliary which both began in 1869, St. Joseph's-by-the-Sea which began in 1910, and Nurse Training which began in 1927.
  The records of the St. Agatha Home for Children are not collected in this series. They are arranged separately as Series V, because the program operated independently from the Foundling from 1884 to 1977. Thereafter, it became a program of the Foundling.
  The scope and content notes for some subseries refer the researcher to other subseries which may also have pertinent information.
  - Subseries IV.1 - Abusing Mother-Child Program/Child Abuse Rehabilitation Program, 1971-1987
    The subseries contains proposals, reports, memos, correspondence, a pamphlet, and photographic prints.
    The Abusing Mother-Child project, subsequently known as the Program for the Rehabilitation of Mothers of Abused and Neglected Children, the Program for Neglecting and Abusing Mothers and Their Children, the Abusing Parents and Child Unit, the Temporary Shelter for Abusing Parents, and finally the Child Abuse Rehabilitation Program was a program designed to give counseling and services to mothers to help stop child abuse, and to keep families together. It began in September 1972, operated in tandem with the Temporary Shelter, and was phased out in 1987.
    For other materials related to child abuse, see Child Abuse Prevention Services, Crisis Nursery, and Fontana Center subseries.
    - Abusing Mother-Child Program - Proposal, Correspondence, 1971 April 12 - 1975 January 20 and undated (Offsite-box 21, Folder 1)
    - Abusing Mother-Child Program/Child Abuse Rehabilitation Program - Reports, Memos, Correspondence, circa 1972 - 1987 March 13 (Offsite-box 21, Folder 2)
    - Abusing Parent and Child Unit - Pamphlet, 1977 (Offsite-box 21, Folder 3)
    - Child Abuse Rehabailitation Program - Special Services for Children document re: budget, organization, 1986 April 22 (Offsite-box 21, Folder 4)
    - Abusing Mother-Child Program Temporary Shelter Therapeutic Nursery - Photographic Prints, 1978 and undated (Offsite-box 21, Folder 5)
  - Subseries IV.2 - Adolescent Girls' Unit, 1976-1981
    This subseries consists of one folder. Further documents regarding the Adolescent Girls Unit are located in Box 22, Folder 15.
    - Adolescent Girls' Unit - Proposal, Reports, Correspondence, 1976 October 5 - 1981 circa December (Offsite-box 21, Folder 6)
  - Subseries IV.3 - Adoption, circa 1911-1999
    This subseries consists of six folders containing correspondence, reports, forms, pamphlets, information about legislation, photographic prints, and clippings related to adoption services at the NY Foundling Hospital.
    Since adoption often occurred in conjunction with "orphan train" or boarding and foster placement, please see these subseries for related materials.
    - Adoption - History, Legislation, Position Papers - Correspondence, Reports, Forms (1 of 2), circa 1911 - 1998 (Offsite-box 21, Folder 7)
    - Adoption - Legislation, Forms, other materials (2 of 2), 1981 - 1999 and undated (Offsite-box 21, Folder 8)
    - Adoption - one child's case from admission through indenture and adoption, 1916 July 5 - 1940 February 6 (Offsite-box 21, Folder 9)
    - Adoption Department Pamphlets, circa 1968, circa 1990's (Offsite-box 21, Folder 10)
    - Adoption - Photographic Prints, 1993 and undated (Offsite-box 21, Folder 11)
    - Adoption - Clippings, 1969, circa 1991 (Offsite-box 21, Folder 12)
  - Subseries IV.4 - Agency-Operated Boarding Homes (AOBH), 1969-1987
    This subseries consists of 2 folders of material related to AOBH run by the Foundling. For other AOBH materials, see the Mother/Child and Staten Island subseries in Series IV, and Series V - St. Agatha Home.
    Agency Operated Boarding Homes (AOBH) are community-based residences for children, teens and young adults who require more intensive social and medical services than traditional or therapeutic foster care settings provide.
    - AOBH - Correspondence, Reports, Memos, 1 Photographic Print, 1969 October 24 - 1980 November 21 and undated (Offsite-box 21, Folder 13)
    - AOBH program for emotionally disturbed young children - Proposal, 1985 July 24 - 1987 December 17 (Offsite-box 21, Folder 14)
  - Subseries IV.5 - Blaine Hall, 1973-2001
    The subseries contains 4 folders, containing reports, correspondence, fliers, photographs, and a blueprint.
    Blaine Hall was a temporary residential center for children aged 6-12 located within the main Foundling building. The program began operating in 1974.
    - Blaine Hall - Planning - Correspondence and Blueprint, 1973 April 6 - 1974 May 7 (Offsite-box 21, Folder 15)
    - Blaine Hall - Fliers, Photograph, Informational Material, circa 1974-2001 (Offsite-box 21, Folder 16)
    - Blaine Hall - Annual Report, 1980 (Offsite-box 21, Folder 17)
    - Blaine Hall - Photographic Prints, 1977, 1999 and undated (Offsite-box 21, Folder 18)
  - Subseries IV.6 - Boarding Department and Foster Care, 1916-1995
    This subseries contains documents related to the Boarding Department, the Homefinding and Placement Departments, which originated as divisions of the Boarding Department, and the Foster Boarding Home Departments of the NY Foundling Hospital, and to foster care in general at the Foundling. Materials include reports, newsletters, pamphlets, correspondence, memos, photographic prints, and clippings.
    Correspondence with Special Services for Children (Box 22, folders 14-17) includes correspondence related to Foundling programs that did not provide foster care services, as well as programs that did. All correspondence is kept in this subseries as per original order.
    From the Foundling's inception to the present day, a large part of the organization's work has involved boarding and foster care services. Many other series and subseries in this collection contain documents relating to boarding and foster care, including but not limited to the Series IV subseries Adoption, AOBH, Blaine Hall, Bronx Community Services, St. Joseph's-by-the-Sea, and the Westchester Office.
    Newsletters of the Association of Foster Parents 1955-1966 may be found in Series VII.
    Restricted volumes of the Boarding Department are located in Series XVI.
    - Reports on boarding mothers and on admitted children, circa 1916-1917 (Offsite-box 22, Folder 1)
    - Boarding Out Dept. - 3 typescript reports on standardization of payments for boarding out children, circa 1920 (Offsite-box 22, Folder 2)
    - Report by James E. Fee to Rev. Robert F. Keegan, Secretary for Charities to the Archbishop, on the Boarding Dept., with recommendations, 1921 March 9 (Offsite-box 22, Folder 3)
    - Boarding Department Reports (in a binder), 1932-1933, 1940, 1946-1949 (Offsite-box 22, Folder 4)
    - Boarding Department Bound Report, 1940 (Offsite-box 22, Folder 5)
    - Boarding Department Bound Report, 1941 (Offsite-box 22, Folder 6)
    - Boarding Department Bound Report, 1942 (Offsite-box 22, Folder 7)
    - Boarding Department Bound Report, 1943 (Offsite-box 22, Folder 8)
    - Boarding Department Bound Report (4 copies), 1944 (Offsite-box 22, Folder 9)
    - Boarding Department Bound Report, 1945 (Offsite-box 22, Folder 10)
    - Boarding Department Report, circa 1950-1958 (Offsite-box 22, Folder 11)
    - Boarding Department/Foster Care - Miscellaneous Materials (blessing, newsletters), 1950-1998 (Offsite-box 22, Folder 12)
    - Boarding Department/Foster Care - Pamphlets and fliers recruiting foster parents, circa 1957-2007 (Offsite-box 22, Folder 13)
    - Correspondence from Special Services for Children (1 of 4), 1973-1976 (Offsite-box 22, Folder 14)
    - Correspondence with Special Services for Children (2 of 4), 1977-1979 (Offsite-box 22, Folder 15)
    - Correspondence with Special Services for Children (3 of 4), 1980-1982 (Offsite-box 22, Folder 16)
    - Correspondence with Special Services for Children (4 of 4), 1983-1988 (Offsite-box 22, Folder 17)
    - Memo - Clothing requirements, requisition forms, and procedures for adopted and boarded foster children, 1976 December 20 (Offsite-box 22, Folder 18)
    - Homefinding/Placement (Foster Boarding Homes) Annual Reports, 1977 and 1980 (Offsite-box 22, Folder 19)
    - Regulations for Foster Care Residential Facilities - N.Y.S. Dept. of Social Services, 1979 November, 1987 February, 1990 December (Offsite-box 22, Folder 20)
    - Foster Care - Proposal developed with Lower East Side Family Union and Welfare Research Inc., circa January 1984 (Offsite-box 22, Folder 21)
    - Foster Care - Foster boarding home program for children with AIDS, 1986-1988 (Offsite-box 22, Folder 22)
    - Foster Care - Memos re: Legislation, 1985-1991 (Offsite-box 23, Folder 1)
    - Foster Care - Memos and correspondence re: Homefinding Intensification, 1987 January-October (Offsite-box 23, Folder 2)
    - Foster Care - Memos re: Boarder Babies, 1987 March 18-June 22 (Offsite-box 23, Folder 3)
    - Foster Care - Report on project on classifying and evaluating foster care programs, 1990 February - 1991 April (Offsite-box 23, Folder 4)
    - Foster Parent Manual, 1990 May 22 (Offsite-box 23, Folder 5)
    - Foster Care Questionnaire, 1995 (Offsite-box 23, Folder 6)
    - Boarding and Foster Care - Photographic Prints, circa 1942-1965 and undated (Offsite-box 23, Folder 7)
    - Boarding and Foster Care - Clippings, 1942-1969 and 2008 (Offsite-box 23, Folder 8)
  - Subseries IV.7 - Bronx Community Services, ca. 1970-2001
    Scope and content
    The Foundling opened an office in the South Bronx in the mid-1960's, to provide foster care and related and preventive services to the Spanish-speaking community there.
    The subseries consists of four folders of materials from this program. See also related materials in IV.27 - Mott Haven Prevention Program.
    - Bronx Community Services - Correspondence, invitations, newsletter, quarterly report, 1976 November 9 - 2000 May 5 (Offsite-box 23, Folder 9)
    - Bronx Community Services - Conference programs and materials, 2000, 2001 (Offsite-box 23, Folder 10)
    - Bronx Community Services - Staff workshop materials, circa 2000-2001 (Offsite-box 23, Folder 11)
    - Bronx Community Services - Photographic Prints, circa 1970-2000 (Offsite-box 23, Folder 12)
  - Subseries IV.8 - Bronx Teen Parenting, 1978-2001
    The subseries contains nine folders of materials including proposals, reports, correspondence, contracts, memos, invitations, brochures, photographic prints, and 20th Anniversary commemorative clocks.
    The Bronx Teen Parenting Program began in 1979 to provide counseling, education in pregnancy prevention and in parenting skills, and referral services to young parents, pregnant youth, and those at risk of becoming pregnant.
    - Bronx Teen Parenting - Proposals, reports, correspondence, 1978 December - 1982 May (Offsite-box 23, Folder 13)
    - Bronx Teen Parenting - Morrisania-Hunts Point Proposal - Special Services for Children, 1981 November - 1982 November (Offsite-box 24, Folder 1)
    - Bronx Teen Parenting - Contract with Dept. of Social Services, 1982 August 19 (Offsite-box 24, Folder 2)
    - Bronx Teen Parenting - Modification of contract with Dept. of Social Services, 1982 December 22 (Offsite-box 24, Folder 3)
    - Bronx Teen Parenting - Correspondence and memos re: funding, 1984 August, September (Offsite-box 24, Folder 4)
    - Bronx Teen Parenting - RFP Preventive Services, 1984 November (Offsite-box 24, Folder 5)
    - Bronx Teen Parenting - memos, reports, invitation, 1991, 1994, 1999, 2001 and undated (Offsite-box 24, Folder 6)
    - Bronx Teen Parenting - Correspondence (program director to Sister Marilda), photographs, programs, invitations for 20th Anniversary, 1999-2000 (Offsite-box 24, Folder 7)
    - Bronx Teen Parenting - Photographic Prints, 1983 and undated (Offsite-box 24, Folder 8)
    - Bronx Teen Parenting - 20th Anniversary commemorative clocks separated to Box 77, 1999 (Offsite-box 77)
  - Subseries IV.9 - Child Abuse Prevention Services (including Child Sexual Abuse Treatment Service), 1983-1999
    The subseries contains proposals, invitations, programs, pamphlet, brochure, memos and photographic prints. For documentation of similar programs, see related subseries: Abusing Mother-Child/Child Abuse Rehabilitation, Crisis Nursery, and Fontana Center.
    Child Abuse Prevention Services (CAPS) was created in July 1987 to provide parenting skills education and group therapy to abusive parents in order to stabilize families, prevent foster care or juvenile justice placement, expedite discharge from foster care, and to prevent and treat child abuse. The Child Sexual Abuse Treatment Service was a component of CAPS.
    - Child Sexual Abuse Treatment Proposal and Guidelines, 1983 and circa 1986-1989 (Offsite-box 24, Folder 9)
    - CAPS - newsletter, invitations, and programs for annual completion celebrations, 1990-1999 (Offsite-box 24, Folder 10)
    - CAPS - Child Sexual Abuse Treatment Grant Proposal, 1990 May 9 (Offsite-box 24, Folder 11)
    - CAPS - Child Sexual Abuse Tratment Service - Memos, brochure, booklets, RFP, circa 1999 and undated (Offsite-box 24, Folder 12)
    - CAPS - Child Sexual Abuse Treatment Service - Photographic Prints, circa 1989-1999 (Offsite-box 24, Folder 13)
  - Subseries IV.10 - Children's Planning Services, 1976-1982
    The subseries contains a manual, memos, and quarterly and annual reports.
    The Children's Planning Services Unit was originally established as the Diligent Search Unit in 1971. It was reorganized as the Children's Planning Services Unit of the Legal Department in 1973. The unit dealt with permanent neglect, abandonment, and subdivision 7 proceedings, to hasten the release of abandoned children so they could be adopted.
    - Children's Planning Services - Manual, 1976 November (Offsite-box 24, Folder 14)
    - Children's Planning Services - Memos, Quarterly and Annual Reports, 1977 December 28 - 1982 January 2 (Offsite-box 24, Folder 15)
  - Subseries IV.11 - Cities in Schools Program, 1979-1984
    The subseries contains one folder. Cities-in-Schools was a federally-funded program that began in 1975, to reduce truancy and prevent pupil drop-out, to coordinate social service delivery to students and families, and to create social service presence in schools. The NY Foundling Hospital subcontracted with Cities-in-Schools 1980-1984.
    - Cities in Schools Program - correspondence, reports, memos, newsletters, 1979-1984 (Offsite-box 24, Folder 16)
  - Subseries IV.12 - Crisis Nursery, 1965-2004 (bulk 1982-2004)